Guide to the Oliver Cromwell, Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
"Oliver Cromwell - autograph letters and historical documents 1646-1658"
OSBORN FB67
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.17
(1 volume)
Collection of letters, documents, printed pieces, and portraits of Cromwell and his associates. Contents include 9 MS of Cromwell, 13 MS of persons associated with Cromwell, 19 printed or engraved broadsides, cartoons, etc., 22 portraits of Cromwell and 20 portraits of his associates.
Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a partial inventory of the contents of Osborn fb67. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658
- Osborn fb67: Partial List
  - CROMWELL, OLIVER, 1599-1658
    - ALS to [?], 1650 Feb 18 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      "My deere freind I perceave by
      Harrison's letter you made me play
      the fool ..."
      67/3
  - CROMWELL, OLIVER, 1599-1658
    - ALS to Bridget (Cromwell) Ireton later Mrs Fleetwood), 1646 Oct 25 (Box 1)
      "Deere Daughter I write not to thy
      husband partly to avoid trouble ..."
      67/7
  - CROMWELL, OLIVER, 1599-1658
    - Document, signed, ordering Sir John Wollaston to make payment to Colonel Culme. Appended is receipt signed by Col. Culme, 1649 Aug 31., 1649 Aug 30 (Box 1)
      [Ireland]
      "These are to require you ... to
      paie Collonell Culme ..."
      67/13
  - SKIPPON, PHILIP, D.1660
    - LS to William Grey, 1st baron Grey of Werke (d.1674), 1645 Jun 21 (Box 1)
      Bosworth
      "My Lord I humbly thanke yr. Lo. for
      taking any notice of my unworthy
      service ..."
      67/17
  - CROMWELL, OLIVER, 1599-1658
    - LS to the Middlesex Magistrates, 1651 Jan 12 (Box 1)
      York
      "Gentlemen, Whereas it is provided
      by severall Acts and ordinances ..."
      Concerns relief for maimed soldiers
      and their dependents.
      67/19
  - CROMWELL, OLIVER, 1599-1658
    - LS to Thomas Harrison (1606-1660), 1651 May 3 (Box 1)
      Edinburgh
      "Dear Harrison I Received thine of
      the 23d of Aprill ..."
      Concerns troop movements.
      67/23
  - FLEETWOOD, CHARLES, D. 1692
    - "Relacon of the Fighte", 1651 Sep 5 (Box 1)
      67/27
  - CROMWELL, OLIVER, 1599-1658
    - LS (in Latin) to the Senate of Geneva, 1655 Jul 28 (Box 1)
      Westminster
      "Tristissimum illud quod de
      sanguinaria Evangelicorum ..."
      Concerning the persecution of
      Protestants in the Vaudois.
      67/35
  - NOTTINGHAM, CHARLES HOWARD, 2ND EARL OF, 1610-1681
    - LS to Edward Montagu, 2nd earl of Manchester (1602-1671), Speaker of the House of Lords., 1647 Jun 26 (Box 1)
      Uxbridge
      "May it please yr. Lor. Wee came
      hither Last Night where wee found
      th Generall ..."
      67/39
  - FAIRFAX, CHARLES
    - LS to an army officer in the West Country, 1647 Aug 5 (Box 1)
      [Thirwall]
      "I shall not bee soo large as I
      intended ..."
      67/41
  - CROMWELL, OLIVER, 1599-1658
    - Document, signed, 1651 Jun 12 (Box 1)
      General pass for Capt. Edward Moore
      and staff.
      67/43
  - SCOT, THOMAS, D.1660
    - LS to the Council of State, 1651 Aug 31 (Box 1)
      Worcester
      Signed jointly by Scot and Major
      R. Salwey.
      67/45
  - LILBURNE, ROBERT, 1613-1665
    - LS to the Council of State, 1652/3 Feb 26 (Box 1)
      67/46
  - BLAKE, ROBERT, 1599-1657
    - LS to the Commissioners of the Navy, 1653 Jun 7 (Box 1)
      67/53
  - CROMWELL, OLIVER, 1599-1658
    - LS to William Boulton, 1655 May 17 (Box 1)
      Whitehall
      "Whereas Wee are informed by the
      Lieutenant of the Tower of
      London ..."
      An order to deliver certain papers
      to John Frost.
      67/63
  - FAUCONBERG, THOMAS BELASYSE, 1ST EARL, 1628-1700
    - ALS to [Lord Burlington], n.y. Aug 26 (Box 1)
      67/67
  - BRADSHAW, JOHN, 1602-1659
    - LS to the Sheriff of Wiltshire, 1649 Aug 26 (Box 1)
    - Whitehall "These are to will and require you [to issue a proclamation concerning Charles Stuart]". 67/73 (Box 1)
  - CROMWELL, OLIVER, 1599-1658
    - LS to the Commissioners of the Admiralty, 1657/8 Mar 16 (Box 1)
      67/79
  - CROMWELL, OLIVER, 1599-1658
    - ALS (litho. facsimile) to Oliver St John, [1643] Sep 11 (Box 1)
      67/83
  - ORRERY, ROGER BOYLE, 1ST EARL OF, 1621-1679
    - LS to Henry Lawrence (1600-1664), 1656 May 8 (Box 1)
      "My Lord I am appointed by his
      Highness Councill here to trouble
      yr. Lo." Concerning affairs in
      Scotland.
      67/87
  - DESBOROUGH, JOHN, 1608-1680
    - ALS to John Clerke, 1654 Mar 17 (Box 1)
      Chard
      "Sir I am come hither this night in
      my way to Exon ..."
      67/88
  - RUSHWORTH, JOHN, 1612?-1690
    - ALS to Richard Cromwell (1626-1712), ca. 1658-1660 (Box 1)
      "may it pleas yo. Highness The poor
      widow came farre short ..."
      67/91